Guide to the Isidore Witmark Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Isidore Witmark Papers,
1903-1939
Witmark, Isidore, 1871-1941.
121 items (1 box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079490
Biographical Note
American music publisher.
Scope and Content
Forty-three letters to Witmark which were taken out of autographed books given to the University by Mr. Witmark. The letters are from leading authors and artists of the world, chief among them John Kendrick Bangs, Harry B. Smith, and Frederick Kummar. They are mostly friendly notes, some of them in connection with Witmark's requests that authors autograph books for his library. Also, eight manuscript music scores written by various composers including Victor Herbert for the wedding of Witmark and Viola Cahn; and printed matter including programs, clippings, and prospectuses, two autographed photographs, and a typescript catalog of the "Autograph Library of Isidore Witmark, Esq."
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 2 series:
Series I: Laid in Correspondence and Clippings
Series II: Autograph Musical Scores
Subjects
Bangs, John Kendrick, 1862-1922.; Smith, Harry Bache, 1860-1936.; Kummar, Frederick.; Herbert, Victor, 1859-1924.; Witmark, Viola Cahn.; Authors.; Artists.; Composers.; Music publishing--United States.; Wedding music.; Photoprints.; Musical scores.; Autographs.; Publishers and publishing.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1941 M-41 Witmark, Isidore Bequest
- Series I: Laid in Correspondence and Clippings
  - Ade, George Clipping, [v.p.], 8 February 1937 (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Forty modern fables]
  - Adler, Felix Clipping, 27 April 1935 (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Creed and deed]
  - Bangs, John Kendrick The word, No. 30, 1908 (Box 1)
  - Baum, Lyman Frank. To Isidore Witmark, Chicago, 19 April 1903, (1 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his By the candelabra's glare]
  - Bloom, Sol To Isidore Witmark, Washington D.C., 12 October 1938 (Box 1)
    [Laid in his The story of the constitution]
  - Burke, Thomas To Isidore Witmark, London, 27 May (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Limehouse nights]
  - Burnett, Frances Hodgson Re Production of Little Lord Fauntleroy, 1889, (1 program, 2 clippings) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Little Lord Fauntleroy]
  - Carvalho, David N. To Isidore Witmark, New York, 16 May 1908, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Forty centuries of ink]
  - Dunbar, Paul Lawrence To a golden girl, 1936, (1 a.ms.) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his The uncalled, a novel]
  - Fagan, Barney Clipping, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box Box 1)
    [Laid in William Devere's Jim Marshall's new planner]
  - Frohman, Daniel Prospectus for his book Encore, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Encore]
  - Grossman, Ethel B. Poem, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 1)
    [Laid in her Poems]
  - Harrison, Mrs. Constance (Cary) [To Isidore Witmark], [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 a.n.s., 1 signed picture) (Box 1)
    [Laid in her A Virginia cousin and Bar Harbor tales]
  - Haydt, Herman A. Re Poems, [n.p.], 26 October 1933, (1 clipping) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Collected poems]
  - Holley, Marietta Marietta Holley's Books, [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 leaflet) (Box 1)
    [Laid in her Samantha]
  - Houdini, Harry (Ehrich Weiss) Portrait, autographed, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Miracle mongers and their methods]
  - Kennedy, Charles Rann We are all brothers, [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 clipping) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his The servant in the house]
  - Klein, Hermann At home card and leaflet, [n.p.], 2 December 1906 (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Thirty years of musical life in London]
  - Kummer, Frederic Arnold To Isidore Witmark, [n.p.], 5 July & 13 Sept 1930, (2 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Gentlemen in Hades]
  - Leavitt, M. B. From Sylain A. Lee, [n.p.], 9 Jan 1906, (1 t.l. (copy)) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Fifty years in theatrical management]
  - Lowell, Juliet To Isidore Witmark, [n.p.], 10 Jan 1936, (1 a.n.s.) (Box 1)
    [Laid in her Dumb belles-lettres]
  - Markham, Edwin Clippings, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box Box 1)
    [Laid in his The man with the hoe and his Gates of Paradise]
  - Morgenthau, Henry Clippings, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 1)
    [Laid in his All in a life-time]
  - Nobles, Milton A Blue Grass Widow., [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 promotion booklet) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Milton Nobles' shop talk]
  - O' Connor, T.P. To Isidore Witmark, New York, [1906], (1 a.l.s., 3 clipping, 1 dinner menu, 1 t.l. (copy) from Pedgrift to Charles Warren) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Lord Beaconsfield]
  - Oursler, Fulton To Isidore Witmark, New York City, 5 Aug 1929 & 12 May 1931, (2 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his The world's delight]
  - Oursler, Mrs. Grace (Perkins) To Isidore Witmark, [n.p.], 10 Oct 1929 - 10 Oct 1929, (3 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
    [Laid in her Angel child and her Personal maid]
  - Perkins, Ray To Al Jolson, [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 a.n.s.) (Box 1)
    [Laid in Arline De Hass's The Jazz Singer]
  - Riley, James Witcomb Clipping, [n.p.], 9 February 1935 (Box 1)
    [Laid in his The boys of the Old Glee Club]
  - Roma, Caro card, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Poems]
  - Romberg, Sigmund To Isidore Witmark, New York, 30 December 1930, (1 t.l.s., 1 program) (Box 1)
  - Ryan, Millie Prospectus for her studios, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 1)
    [Laid in her What every singer should know]
  - Smith, Harry Bache To Isidore Witmark, New York City, 1931-1935, (3 a.l.s., 2 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his First nights and first editions, his Lyrics and sonnets, and his Stage lyrics]
  - Sonneck, O.G. To Isidore Witmark, [n.p.], 26 Feb 1927, (1 t.l.s., 1 clipping) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Beethoven letters in America]
  - Sousa, John Philip To Isidore Witmark, [n.p.], 30 Nov 1945, (1 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Pipetown Sandy]
  - Springer, Thomas Grant To Isidore Witmark, [n.p.], 1938-1939, (1 t.l.s. from Herman Heydt, 1 typed poem signed, 1 p.c.) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Rodeo, and his The Red Cord]
  - Taylor, Deems The Kings Henchmen, [n.p.], 1927 & 1931, (1 libretto, 1 program, several clippings) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his The kings henchman]
  - Thomas, Lowell Clippings, [n.p.], 1930 (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Count Luckner, the sea devil]
  - Tyler, George C. To Isidore Witmark, [n.p.], 13 March 1934, (1 t.l.s) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Whatever goes up]
  - Valeria, Julie, and James Young To Isidore Witmark, [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 a.p.c.s., 1 program, 1 clipping) (Box 1)
  - Weber, Joe and Lew Fields Clipping, [n.p.], 4 September 1938 (Box 1)
    [Laid in Isman's Weber and Fields]
  - Weeks, Edward This trade of writing, [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 review) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his This trade of writing]
  - Wilder, Marshall Pinckney To Isidore Witmark, New York City, [n.d.] & 15 Jan 1909, (2 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his The people I've smiled with]
  - Wilson, Francis Clipping, [n.p.], 1 November 1925 (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Joseph Jefferson]
  - Wilstach, Paul To Isidore Witmark, Ginston, VA & New York, 1909-1912, (3 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
    [Laid in his Richard Mansfield, the man and the actor]
  - Wister, Owen Clipping, [n.p.], 21 June 1935 (Box 1)
    [Laid in his The Virginian]
  - Columbia University Libraries Catalog of the Isidore Witmark Collection of Autographed Books and Musical Scores, New York, March 1942 (Box 1)
- Series II: Autograph Musical Scores
  - Ball, Ernest R. To the end of the world with you, [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 a.ms.s.) (Box 2)
  - Edwards, Julian Love's harmony, [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 a.ms.s.) (Box 2)
  - Herbert, Victor Wedding music composed for Witmark and Viola Cahn, [n.p.], 24 December 1908, (1 a.ms.s.) (Box 2)
  - Klein, Manuel Serenade to Viola, New York, 14 Dec 1908, (1 a.ms.s.) (Box 2)
  - Klein, Manuel The proud prince, [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 a.ms.s.) (Box 2)
  - Luders, Gustav Waltz, wedding bells, [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 a.ms.s.) (Box 2)
  - Mann, Nathaniel D. The bride's dream waltz, [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 a.ms.s.) (Box 2)
  - Northrup, Theodore March canopy, Omaha, Nebraska, 18 Januray 1909, (1 a.ms.s.) (Box 2)
  - Witmark, Isidore Little woman of the west, [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 a.ms.s.) (Box 2)